The IDE is dying and so is tool calling.
OpenAI is not going to win. And next
year, you're going to be shipping code
that you've never reviewed before, even
as an experienced engineer. Because let
me tell you, the way that we use AI in
2026 for coding and agents is going to
look completely different. And so, in
this video, I want to quickly cover my
predictions with you and why they matter
right now. And some of these are
definitely going to be hot takes. So,
let me know in the comments if you
disagree with anything. I am genuinely
curious. And before we dive in, yes, I
have partially lost my voice. I'm sure
you can tell, but I'm still really
excited to get into all this with you.
All right, so for the first prediction,
idees are dead, at least as we know it,
because traditional IDEs where the code
is the focus of the interface is simply
going to become irrelevant. We're so
hyperfocused on orchestrating different
AI agents. So, we're moving towards more
of an agent manager interface where we
can kick off agents in parallel to work
on different features in a codebase or
even work on different projects at the
exact same time. And we're already
starting to see this with Google's
anti-gravity, for example. They have a
traditional IDE component, but they also
have this agent manager where we can
kick off these different work requests
for our agents across different code
bases. We can review things just like we
would with a GitHub PR and we can have
our comments here that it'll address in
real time. It's really really cool. And
cursor with their new 2.0 update, they
also have something like this. And then
we have options in the cloud like codeex
web and cloud code for the web where we
can do this kind of orchestration as
well. It's so high leverage. We can kick
off all these different agents to work
for us at the same time. On top of that,
I'm also working on my own custom remote
agentic coding system. So, I can inject
my own process for planning,
implementing, and validating like you're
looking at right here. And I can do this
in pretty much any application, GitHub,
Telegram. I'm working on a Slack
integration. It's so cool. And the best
part is I am giving away this complete
system to you, but only in a live stream
that I'm doing this Saturday, November
29th, at 9:00 a.m. Central time. So,
come be a part of it. It's going to be a
blast. I'm going to give away this
entire system and show you how to use it
because this my friend really is the
future of agentic coding where we can
interact with our agents wherever we
actually do our work. So with that on to
the next prediction here the different
paths to AI dominance. A lot of people
think that in the future a single large
language model is going to have a
monopoly and be the best at absolutely
everything. But what really is going to
happen is different providers are going
to specialize and focus on being the
best at different things. And we're
already seeing this with Google, for
example, going down the more generalist
play. They just want to be the jack of
all trades. Anthropic is focusing on
being the best for coding. And we can
even see this with the benchmarks.
Gemini 3 is just crushing it across the
board. And then Opus 4.5 comes out. And
of course, the first benchmark they show
is the one for software engineering
because that is what Anthropic is
focusing on. and other providers are
going to come up with models that are
more focused on something like creative
tasks. We're going to have that
specialization more and more where it
depends what we're building that will
determine the LLM that we use
specifically. But you know who I don't
think is going to come out on top with
any kind of specialization is OpenAI.
And this is probably the biggest hot
take in this entire video, but they just
disappointed time and time again with
GPT 5.1 and 5 and GPT [clears throat]
4.5. with 4.5, they seem to like try to
be that creative specialist, but it just
really didn't work. And there's so many
more LLMs, especially open source ones
that are focused on that. And so, I
don't know, maybe they're going to come
on top literally next month and GBT6 is
going to be released, and it's going to
be absolutely killer. But so far,
they've been hyping up so many different
things, and it's never ended up being a
huge breakthrough. And speaking of more
LLMs being available, next up we have
the local AI breakthrough. I really do
believe that 2026 is going to be the
year of local AI. We didn't see that
much this year besides Deep Seek at the
start of 2025. I mean, that was a big
deal, but then there wasn't really
anything more as far as local AI. We had
a couple of new models like Quen 3, but
nothing super super big. But we are
starting to see some new hardware come
out that is making it obvious that we
are going to start to be able to run
very large models even on smaller
devices. I'll have a link to this
article in the description. There is a
new AI chip that apparently is going to
be able to run upwards of 120 billion
parameter large language models on the
edge which would be a complete gamecher
because right now the hardware
requirements is one of the biggest
problems when it comes to scaling local
AI. And so if we can solve the problem
of hardware then we have 100% data
privacy and zero millisecond latency for
our agents. And that is the dream. And
going back to the theme of AI coding, we
are finally going to get to the point
where we are not the coders. We delegate
that entirely to our coding agents and
we are the system architects. And I'm
already doing that myself. That's what
I'm teaching on my channel in the
Agentic coding course. But it's finally
going to become mainstream where we
instead focus on the highlevel design,
architecture, and validation of our AI
coding system. And it's interesting
because this actually mirrors the
evolution of other engineering
disciplines. For example, civil
engineers, they don't fabricate the
steel beams. They design the structure
and verify the integrity. And that's
exactly where we're going as software
engineers as well. And I like to think
of this as a three-step process. We
define our objectives and the system
that our agents will operate under. And
then we orchestrate by delegating the
coding to our agents. And then we
validate the outputs and ensure the
quality of the overall system
afterwards. And so we're still in the
loop. We are the final say in whatever
is created, but we're delegating the
grunt work, all the coding to our coding
agents. The sponsor of today's video is
none other than Postman themselves, the
API platform. Basically, every dev under
the sun has used Postman to test,
manage, and deploy APIs. But did you
know that they are now helping you build
APIs for your AI agents, which is
something that people do not focus on
enough? 57% of organizations say that AI
has increased the number of APIs that
they manage. And the reason for that is
when you deploy an agent to production,
it's sitting behind an API and then also
using APIs for the tools. And so APIs
are no longer just the infrastructure.
They're a strategic backbone for your
agents. And so making sure that your
APIs are robust is equally if not more
important than the rest of building your
agent like selecting the model for
example. And so Postman makes it
possible for us. And what they have here
is the 90-day AI readiness playbook,
your guide to building this API
infrastructure for your agents. So I
will link to this guide in the
description. It's definitely worth the
time investment. If you don't put time
into developing API readiness, I can
promise you that your agents are going
to fall into chaos when they're deployed
in production. And Postman gives us a
lot more than just their guide. They
have an AI agent builder when here we
can build productionready AI agents
sitting behind the Postman API
infrastructure. They have a ton of
templates for you to get started. You
can obviously make your own as well. You
have this low/nood builder that makes it
really easy to stitch things together to
build any agent that you want. They have
their agent mode to help us build and
test things as well. And then when we
deploy our agent, this is the best part
that really leverages Postman. We have
all of the monitoring and performance
metrics, the dashboard to set up alerts,
all of the production ready
infrastructure that we'd expect from
Postman. So, I will have a link in the
description to the Postman AI agent
builder because if you are serious about
building productionready AI agents and
APIs, you should definitely check this
out. And our agents themselves are also
going to change a lot next year because
code execution is starting to replace
tool calling because the problem we have
with tool calling right now is that all
the capabilities that we give our agent,
they have to take context upfront. And
so when you try to give a lot of
different tools to an agent, you
completely overwhelm it. And so code
execution is a massive token reduction.
It's also faster and more flexible
because essentially what you're doing is
you are giving the agent the ability to
generate its own capabilities at runtime
by writing the code to interact with the
API or whatever it needs to do. And this
article from Anthropic I will link in
the description. They talk all about the
problem with tools in MCP and how code
execution is the solution. I definitely
think that this is where we're heading
with agents so we can make them a lot
more nimble and lean. And the best part
about the flexibility of code execution
is it unlocks the next level of
progressive disclosure. I know that
sounds like a fancy term, but all I mean
by that is we have a lot of capabilities
for an agent, but we don't actually give
all of them to the agent upfront.
Instead, we allow the agent to discover
the capabilities and then leverage them
in a more flexible way. And so what that
looks like is for each capability, we
just have a bit of metadata or a
description that we load up front. And
then when the agent zooms in on that
description, it says,"I want to leverage
that capability." Then we will load in
the full instructions. That might
include scripts or a guide on how to
generate the code for that tool,
whatever that might be. And so now we
can practically scale to infinity
because all of these capabilities don't
have to be loaded at runtime. It's just
this tiny description. And if you want a
really good example of this, take a look
at Claude skills. It's kind of the first
standard for composable skills or
progressive disclosure. And I know I
know I've been focusing a lot on
Enthropic and Claude in this video, but
they really are on the forefront with
their research. And so this is a brief
diagram that explains how skills work.
And this is focused on an AI coding
assistant, but skills apply to literally
any kind of AI agent. So you start with
your main context. This is what you
always have loaded for your model like
traditional tools or your global rules
whatever that might be. But then you
have this skill discovery. So based on
just that tiny description that you give
at first if the agent decides to
leverage a skill and then you load the
instructions on demand. So you start
with what is called a skill.md. This is
the primary instruction set for the
skill that tells it how to write the
code or other references or scripts to
leverage. And then you can also pull in
these reference files, but only when you
need them. And so there's actually
multiple layers here. You pull in the
skill.md. And then you might also decide
to pull in the forms.m MD. So you have
this progressive loading of all of this
context that you need for your
capabilities. That's why it's called
progressive disclosure. So I talked
about how local AI is something that
really wasn't that big this year, even
though I thought it was going to be. And
agent to Asian protocols is another
really good example of that. So this is
the kind of thing where we have AI
agents that operate in a peer network.
They can discover each other's
capabilities in real time and interact
very autonomously. And there's a lot of
potential here. And I thought that is
going to be a really big thing,
especially when Google released their
A2A protocol earlier this year. I made a
video on it. There was a ton of buzz
when it first came out and a lot of
people thought it was going to be the
next big standard, like the next MCP.
But then nothing happened with it and it
kind of just completely fell to the
wayside. And I think one of the big
reasons for that is that we have sort of
a chicken and egg problem with A2A or
any agent agent protocol. In order for
it to be useful, we have to have a lot
of people adopt it at the same time.
Otherwise, if we build an agent that is
A2A compatible, then it has no other
agents to talk to. So the whole value
proposition is lost unless we already
have this big network that we can attach
to right away. But I think that next
year that is finally going to happen,
especially because of my next big
prediction here is that machines paying
machines is going to become a very big
thing. And Coinbase recently released a
protocol for this called X42. It's a way
for us to build AI agents that we expose
over the internet, but we require
payment whenever someone else interacts
with them. And this goes really well
with agent to agent because we can
create this kind of peer network where
we monetize our agents. They are all
leveraging each other but making
payments whenever they are taking
advantage of the capabilities of another
agent. And so we can make money with our
agents assuming it exposes capabilities
that other people want to leverage
through their AI agents. And this is
naturally a coinbased protocol because
cryptocurrency is just the perfect
solution as the payment mechanism for
these kind of machineto-achine networks.
We need a currency where it's really
easy to do micro payments quickly and
globally. And we want something pretty
stable overall. So, a stable coin like
USDC is the perfect option for this. And
out of all the predictions that I have
here, this is probably the newest
concept. But I do think that this is
going to be something that is going to
be pretty widespread starting next year.
All right, for the last two predictions
here, I want to go back to AI coding
because I really do believe that coding
is the most high lever use case for
regenerative AI. And so my next
prediction is artifact reviews instead
of diff reviews. And so in a very
traditional sense, when we want to do a
vigorous code review, we're going to
look at line by line all of the changes
that were made by the human or AI
engineer. But coding agents are starting
to get to the point where they have full
capabilities to show us the proof in the
pudding. So instead of us having to
review things line by line, we can look
at browser recordings they send us and
this goes with remote agentic coding
systems where it could just like send
that to us in GitHub or in Slack full
working demos of a backend API. And so
we can rely on these to know that the
coding assistant did the job well
instead of having to do a full code
review. And if you want an example of
browser recordings, we can go back to
Google's anti-gravity that I showed
earlier because they have Google Chrome
directly integrated in the IDE now. So,
as a part of its coding process, it can
autonomously spin up your website, visit
it, scroll through it, take screenshots,
and everything. You can even view the
playback afterwards like I'm doing right
here. So, it can visually verify your
front end and make sure that your
application is working properly. So,
this is a good example of what I mean by
artifact review. And it's so much nicer.
We can take a look at this to make sure
everything is working well instead of
having to get into all the diffs. And so
for the very last prediction that I have
for you, we really are tying a lot of
things together because we've talked
about reviewing artifacts instead of
diffs and creating systems instead of
coding, the new capabilities we're going
to have for agents with things like code
execution. And so we're going to get to
the point very quickly where we're going
to be shipping code that we have never
read before. And yes, I understand that
people who vibe code are already doing
this, but I'm saying even experienced
engineers are going to get to the point
where they trust their system so much
that they have the ability to review the
code, but they're not going to. We're
just going to be shipping things to
production after we review those
artifacts that we have. And so I'm not
saying that we're going to take the
human completely out of the loop, but
I'm saying that we're going to have a
lot of trust in our system and a
validation process set up that includes
us. That doesn't necessarily have to be
us actually looking at the code. And I
definitely look forward to that. And
that's really what I'm building towards
every single day with the things that
I'm showing you on my channel and what
I'm doing in the Dynamis community. And
so there you go. That's everything I
have as far as predictions with AI going
into 2026. And please let me know in the
comments what you think. I'm active in
the comments every single day, so I will
respond to you. And I want to know if
you agree with everything or if you
think something that I covered in here
is just a pile of garbage. And so with
that, if you appreciate this video and
you're looking forward to more things on
AI agents and AI coding, I would really
appreciate a like and a subscribe. and I
will see you in the next video.